All right, now we have an idea of how do we define a method, how do we declare it and how do we
call it, right? Now the second part comes in about the parameters and I'll just walk you through a
real world problem where we would be stuck and there we would use parameters to rescue us, right?
I'll not get through it in a theoretical fashion but in a more handsome fashion as you have been
seeing right across the core course until now and you will see me doing that later on as well.
So now just to make it a realistic example, what I'll do is I'll just create a new
class. Let me call it, for example, calculate addition. All right, so again the customary
main method, now just imagine a scenario where we have got a requirement, we have to add two numbers,
take them from runtime and print its result, right? So this would be a great example as it evolves,
just have a look at it. So how would I do that, right? So what I'll do is I'll have a method
and just call it white it, two numbers, appropriate meaning, right? And obviously how do you get
numbers from runtime, you know it now, you know the trail that is through the scanner class and
now let's say scanner from Java to detail, I'll just call it scan to new scanner and I'll say
system dot it. Okay, and I'll just ask the user to enter two numbers that are required for
editing and I'll just take them into variables. I'll say int first num to scan dot next int and I'll
just copy paste this line, I'll say int second num, right? I took the two numbers and now I do
the addition, I'll say int result to first num addition second. And I'll just go ahead and print that,
I'll say addition of numbers is and I'll say result. That's it, simple program takes two numbers,
does the addition and prints the result to the screen. Obviously it will not do anything if I don't
call it and you know the trail and I'll do the efficient way, I'll just create an object without a
reference variable because why do I need it? Because I don't have to do anything with that object
after this line. So let's just do new calculate addition, that's the name of the class and I'll say
dot directly at two numbers, that's it. So the control would flow like from main, it would go to
at two numbers and just come back to main and exit your program as well. Let's go on and on this
and as expected, it says enter two numbers. I'll say 101, I'll say 235, it says addition of numbers
is 336. Let's run this again and I'll say 12, I'll say 899, that gives me the right addition,
that is eight, nine, nine, one, one mostly. So works fine, perfectly fine, right? But there's the
problem, the problem is I put in all the code in eight two numbers, right? And that is not
good programming practice as I told you debugging is harder, code maintenance is harder and also
doesn't look good as well because you've just put everything inside just one chunk of code
called a method. That is eight two numbers. So generally because it just says eight two numbers,
it should just add the numbers and not take them from runtime. That's why I'll just get this part
out of it and put that for now inside me, but you can just go ahead and create one more method
for taking input, right? Divide it further. But for now, just to get started, I've used scanner
inside me, ask the user to enter two numbers, take those two numbers, put them into two variables
and then I'll just like to pass them to eight two numbers on a platter so that it's ready to
add what it was always supposed to be doing. And for that purpose, I can now put in parameters.
I told you you can put in zero parameters as I did until now and you can put in one to end
parameters as well depending on your requirement and how many parameters do I have a requirement
to put in here? You're right. That is two and I'll just call them in first num and in second.
And say, I'll just do the addition here and then just the result. So this would be done.
So what would happen? But this is an error because why at the time I'm calling it two numbers,
arguments and parameters do not match. And the rule says the arguments and the parameters
should always match. So what I'll do is I'll pass these first number and second number,
two at two numbers, the copies are passed, the values are passed, and then this first
num and second num takes them and adds them and prints that on the on the screen. So a note here
is that wouldn't it give me an error that I'm just calling this first num and second num the same
as I'm calling a line of 16? Wouldn't that be a conflict of naming? No, it would not. Why? Because
go back to the previous video where I was talking about levels of variables, right? So this
first num and second num are defined with the ball within the body of main. That means these are
local variables of main can only be accessed until line number 14. So add two numbers,
doesn't know anything about these first and second, it only knows about first num and second
num, which are its own local variables that can be accessed until line number 22. So they say,
if it ain't broken, why fix it? So and the good programming practices, we should not call it
f and it's second and no. If it ain't broken, why fix it for better readable, you just adding
first them and second num. So just keep them the same. All right. So let's run this now for the end
user. Let's see if it does make any differences into two numbers. I'll say 12 and 76 gives me the
right result. Additional numbers is 88. The end user doesn't feel a difference, but in programming
style, this is a better version that is the second version of addition of two numbers because now
I've got one burden less in eight to numbers. Still, it's doing much more than what it was expecting
expected to do. That is it was just expected to a two numbers, but it's also printing it. So what
I can do is I can get this out of here. And I can say return. Right. And the key word return is used
to return back a value from a method. And the rule is a method can only return one value back,
not two, not three, nothing else, just one value. Right. So I've returned result, but it says that
the return type is wide. Wide means this method cannot return anything, but you're returning a
value that is of type in there's a clash. So the moment you put in the return, you have to change
the return type to the type, the value that you're returning off. So I'll say this time it's
a in the compiler is happy. Right. In result, return result, write this and the type of this variable
should match or the value should match. And then if you do it like this, this value would be lost
because you've not taken it back. This method, I two numbers, you called it, it sent back a value with
it, but you're not caught it. So it's lost. So in order to that being not lost, you have to catch it,
I'll say it in result. See, right here, local variable of main and then just go on and write it.
Let's say the same thing. I think I copied that. Yeah, I missed it. And now this method is doing
what it was supposed to doing all the way along. That is just adding numbers, not taking
numbers from runtime, not printing them on screen, just adding and it's just doing that. You
know, immediately debugging would be a lot easier and better organization of code as well.
Let's see if this works. I'll just run this to the end user. The third version of my additional
program should make no differences and doesn't make 134 plus two is 136 in fact. Right. And you can
even shorten it further now in instead of doing it two lines. Once you understand, as I told you
before, the two line syntax, just do it at one line. I'll say directly a return first number, second
number, just add and return one line of code this. Right. So once you've got a grasp of the two
line, a three line, you're all long listed code, then try to strive for writing shorter,
succinct code, which is less verbose. Right. Just return it directly. And I don't even need this here.
I can just directly go in and just put this in a cell. See, I can see
with concatenation, addition of numbers is that said, let's get rid of this. You call that method,
pass the parameters past the arguments. And then was the result is fetched back that it finds
itself in a print and then statement and just split that on the screen. See, the fourth version
of my same program is entered to numbers. I'll say 12 78. Right result for versions, but this is the
better. This is the best version yet. But you can go ahead and create one or two merge versions.
Again, think about it. That is, can you get rid of this? Taking the user input from runtime from
main, because now main is overburdened. The role of main is just to act as an entry point,
call a two numbers and exit. That's it. It's role should never have been taking numbers
and printing that. Can you create two more methods for me after this video for
taking numbers and printing them on screen so that main is also less burdened. But that is how
we use parameters. That's how we use return types. If you're returning a value that's of type
float, you have to put the return type float. If you're returning a value that's of type
care, you have to put the return type as care. If you're returning a string value,
the return type has to be string. If you're returning an object of a class, the return type has to
be the class type here. That's the rule. It should match. Right. So, and that is about methods
in details. Right. With or without parameters or with a return type or just keeping it wide,
again, depending on the circumstance and the situation, you find yourself in,
you're going to make that decision at when you're trying to write code yourself.